Mss.B.Sca42
American Philosophical Society
- Series IV. Military, legal,and financial documents, 1459-1847 October 22; 142.0 folders
  - Obligation, 1752 October 20; 1.0 item (Box 6, Folder 42)
    The full title reads, "Obligation consentie par Massire Joseph Juste Cezer Lescalle de Veronne Escuyer en faveur de Monsieur Etienne Derrenyuer"
  - Lescale de Vérone, Joseph Juste Caesar de- will, 1755 February 26; 1.0 item (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Lescale de Vérone, Marie Catherine de- certificate of baptism, 1755 August 4; 1.0 item (Box 6, Folder 44)
    Although the text reads that the baptism took place on 1753 August 17, the document is dated 1755 August 4.
    Lescale de Vérone, Marie Catherine de, 1753-1768
  - Collection of legal documents, 1759 October 24-1763 August 6; 11.0 items (Box 6, Folder 45)
    This folder contains eleven different documents from a range of years.
  - Bousquet, Louise- certificate of baptism, 1760 August 26; 1.0 item (Box 6, Folder 46)
    Louise, Bosquet
  - Lescale de Vérone, Louis Francoise de- military charge, 1765 February 14; 1.0 item (Box Oversize 3, Folder 13)
    Lescale de Vérone, Louis Francois de, 1747-
  - Collection of documents- photographed copies, 1765 April 8-1825 June 3; 8.0 items (Box Oversize 3, Folder 14)
    This is a collection of eight photographs taken of original documents created from 1765 April 8 to 1825 June 3. The handwriting is, at times, difficult to read but the documents seem to relate most directly to Mademoiselle Victoire de Vérone and her immediate family, including her mother and her inheritance in Santo Domingo.
    These documents were grouped in the same original folder as "Documents relating to the slaves belonging to the Lescale de Verone family- copies"
    Louise, Bosquet; Poizat; Vérone, Victoire de
  - Lescale de Vérone, Marianne Josephe de and Lescale de Vérone, Elizabeth Hariette de- certificate of baptism, 1766 July 13; 1.0 item (Box 6, Folder 47)
    Although the text reads that the baptism of Marianne Josephe de Lescale de Veronne took place on 1746 September 18 and the baptism of Elizabeth Hariette de Lescale de Veronne on 1749 October 1, the document is dated 1766 July 13.
    Lescale de Verone, Elizabeth Hariette de; Lescale de Vérone, Marianne Josephe de
  - Lescale de Vérone, Louis Francois de- certificate of baptism, 1767 October 30; 1.0 item (Box 6, Folder 48)
    Although the text reads that the baptism took place on 1747 August 24, the document is dated 1767 October 30.
  - Vérone de Lescale, Marie Joseph Catherine de- death certificate, 1768 February 14; 1.0 item (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Vente de la metairie de la garde connaître par M. L'abbé de Grossolles, 1770 August 18; 1.0 item (Box 6, Folder 50)
    The full title reads, "Vente de la metairie de la garde connaître par M. L'abbé de Grossolles comme fondé de prouration de M. l'abbé de Veronne en faveur de M. de la ville Lieutenant Général"
  - Document, 1787 May 10; 1.0 item (Box 6, Folder 51)
    This is a rectangle of parchment with text written in Latin and signatures at the bottom.
  - Documents relating to the slaves belonging to the Lescale de Verone family- photographed copies, 1789 May 20; 6.0 items (Box Oversize 3, Folder 13)
    These documents were grouped in the same original folder as "Collection of documents- photographed copies"
  - Formal statement about the de Lescale and Poizat families and Santo Domingo, 1843 December 15; 3.0 items (Box 6, Folder 52)
    There are three handwritten copies of the same statement in this folder.
  - Poizat, Jean Robert- note on intention to obtain royal authorization to add de Lescale de Verone to his name, circa 1847; 1.0 item (Box 6, Folder 53)
    Froyez, Alexandre; Poizat, Jean Robert, 1803-1868 July 18
  - Reciept of a shipment of a case of documents from Agen to Paris, 1847 October 22; 1.0 item (Box 6, Folder 54)
    Poizat, Jean Robert, 1803-1868 July 18; Vérone, Victoire de
- Series V: Material in French and Latin- untranslated, 17.0 folders
  - Document 1, 1.0 item (Box 7, Folder 1)
    See also, "Document 5"
    This manuscript begins with the words, "Je Blaise de Bearn" and as a result could be a personal testimony. It is a small packet of papers (about six inches by eight inches) written in a looping cursive. Some sentances are underlined.
  - Document 2, 1.0 item (Box 7, Folder 2)
    See also, "Document 8"
    This document is a single sheet of parchment that looks like some of the earlier documents and "Document 8." It begins with the same "sachent tous."
  - Document 3, 1.0 item (Box 7, Folder 3)
    See also, "Document 6"
    This document is a small sheet of paper with a short paragraph or block text written on it. The first line mentions "Julle de Lescale." The handwriting seems most similar to the earlier manuscripts and looks like "Document 6."
  - Document 4, 1.0 item (Box 7, Folder 4)
    There is a note on the back, which seems to read, "a quit par lequel fait foy du rachat de la rante de ma grant maison a la porte a georga." The document also begins with the name Francois.
  - Document 5, 1.0 item (Box 7, Folder 5)
    See also, "Document 1," which also references de Bern
    This document begins by mentioning the de Bern family from Italy. The years 1259 and 1371 are mentioned as well as the "famille noble de Verone", Scaligeros, and members of the de Scala family. This document could be forming connections between the Scaliger family and their predecessors in Italy.
  - Document 6, 1.0 item (Box 7, Folder 6)
    See also, "Document 3"
    This document looks similar to "Document 3." It mentions de Lescale and Agen.
  - Document 7, 1.0 item (Box Oversize 5, Folder 1)
    This document begins by naming noble Joseph de Lescale and "son plainte." Without a date it is difficult to know which Joseph de Lescale the document references. It also mentions other members of the Scaliger family including Julius Caesar de Lescale. It is signed Joseph de Lascale.
    This document can be found in Oversize Box 5.
  - Document 8, 1.0 item (Box Oversize 5, Folder 1)
    Like "Document 2" this document is written on parchment and begins with "sachent tous"
    See also, "Document 2"
  - Document 9, 1.0 item (Box 7, Folder 7)
    This document is addressed "A Monsieur le Saneschal d'Agennois d'ascoigne...pour le Roy..." There are two paragraphs (perhaps two different messages) written on this same sheet of paper in two different ink colors and two different handwriting.
  - Document 10, 1.0 item (Box 7, Folder 8)
    There are two different paragraphs written on the same piece of paper. While the handwriting looks the same the second paragraph is in a slightly lighter color ink. Agen is mentioned.
  - Document 11, 1600s; 1.0 item (Box 7, Folder 9)
    The document begins with "la partie de Joseph de Lescalle escuyer..." and also mentions Anne de Lescalle, his mother daughter of Julius Caesar de Lescalle, as well as the will of Julius Caesar de Lescale. It is a small booklet of fourteen sheets of paper tied together with string. Some passages of the text are underlined and there are numbers written in the margins.
    Charrier de Lescale de Vérone, Joseph Juste de; Lescale de Vérone, Anne de, after 1528-1619; Scaliger, Julius Caesar, 1484-1558
  - Document 12, 1.0 item (Box 7, Folder 10)
    This document is written in Latin on parchment and at one time had a seal attached to it. It mentions, in bold, Sylvium Cesarem Schaligerum, which could be a reference to Sylvius, Julius Caesar Scaliger's first son. It looks very similar to "Document 13."
    See also, "Document 13"
  - Document 13, 1.0 item (Box 7, Folder 11)
    This document looks very similar to "Document 12." It too is written on parchment in Latin and mentions, in bold, Sylvium Cesarem Scaligerum, which could be a reference to Sylvius, Julius Caesar Scaliger's first son.
  - Document 14, 2.0 items (Box Oversize 5, Folder 3)
    There are two sheets of paper within this folder. The first is ripped at the bottom cutting off the end of the text. The other also has a rip in the middle of it but it does not seem to eliminate any text. Both documents mention the king.
  - Document 15, circa 1500-1550; 1.0 item (Box Oversize 5, Folder 4)
    This is a large rectangle of parchment. There is a small drawing at the bottom and it looks similar to several of the other oversize documents dating from the early 1500s found in Oversize Box 2.
  - Document 16, circa 1500-1550; 1.0 item (Box Oversize 5, Folder 5)
    This is a large rectangular shaped sheet of parchment with three small drawings at the bottom that could be family insignia. It looks similar to several of the other oversize documents dating from the early 1500s found in Oversize Box 2.
  - Document 17, 1.0 item (Oversize Map Room, Folder 5)